Register of the Alfred Hermann Fried Papers, 1914-1921
Hoover Institution Archives
Alfred Hermann Fried Papers,
1914-1921
XX300
Fried, Alfred Hermann, 1864-1921
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diaries, correspondence, clippings, and notes, relating to the international peace movement, particularly during World War I, pacifism, international cooperation, and the World War I war guilt question.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
International cooperation.; Pacifism.; Peace.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Causes.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; Austria.
Biographical Note
1864, Nov. 21 Born, Vienna, Austria
1892 co-founded, with Bertha von Suttner, the the pacifist periodical Die Waffen Nieder (Lay Down Your Arms), from 1899 Die Friedenswarte fuer Zwischenstaatliche Organization (The Peace Watch for International Organization)
1894 Author, Friedenskatechismus (Catechism of Peace)
1899 Author, Die Haager Konferenz, ihre Bedeutung, ihre Ergebnisse (The Haag Conference, its Meaning, its Results)
1905 Author, Das Handbuch der Friedensbewegung (Handbook of the Peace Movement)
1908 Author, Das Internationale Leben der Gegenwart (International Living in a Modern World)
1910 Author, Pan-Amerika (Pan-America)
1911 Winner, Nobel Peace Prize
1912 Die Grundlagen des Ursaechlichen Pazifismus (The Basics of Causative Pacifism)
1914 Emigrated to Switzerland
1914-1918 Editor, Blaetter fuer Internationale Verstaendigung und Zwischenstaatliche Organization (Papers for International Understanding and Inter-State Organization)
1918 Author, Der Weltprotest Gegen den Versailler Frieden (The Global Protest Against the Versailles Treaty)
1918-1920 Author, Mein Kriegstagebuch (My War Diary), 4 volumes
1921 Died, Vienna, Austria
1925 Author, Jugenderinnerungen (Childhood Memoirs), published posthumously
Series Description
- DIARIES, 1914-1919. (Box Boxes 1-2)
  Original diaries of Alfred H. Fried, arranged chronologically.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1914-1919. (Box 3)
  Correspondence of Alfred H. Fried, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
- WRITINGS, ca. 1910-1919. (Box 4)
  Drafts, manuscripts and notes by Alfred H. Fried, arranged alphabetically by title.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1919. (Box Boxes 4-5)
  Newspaper clippings, articles, pamphlets arranged alphabetically by author or title within subseries of Alfred H. Fried's own subject headings, arranged alphabetically.
- MISCELLANY, ca. 1900-1914. (Box 5)
  One scrapbook.
Container List
- DIARIES, 1914-1919
  - August 7 - September 13, 1914 (Box 1)
  - September 13 - October 30, 1914
  - November 2 - December 9, 1914
  - December 9, 1914 - January 12, 1915
  - January 13 - April 29, 1915
  - May 1 - July 10, 1915
  - July 10 - October 26, 1915
  - October 26, 1915 - February 14, 1916
  - February 14 - June 16, 1916
  - June 16 - November 2, 1916
  - November 3, 1916 - March 11, 1917 (Box 2)
  - March 11 - July 3, 1917
  - July 4 - October 27, 1917
  - October 27, 1917 - March 20, 1918
  - March 22 - June 21, 1918
  - June 21 - October 27, 1918
  - October 29, 1918 - April 23, 1919
  - April 24 - June 30, 1919
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1914-1919
  - Unidentified (18) (Box 3)
  - Anonymous, n.d. (1)
  - Angell, Norman, 1918 (1)
  - L'Art Libre, 1919 (2)
  - Bajer, Fredrik, 1914-1918 (5)
  - Bardacs, (?), 1916 (1)
  - Bernstein, Eduard, 1914 (2)
  - Borngraeben, Dr. Otto, 1915 (1)
  - Brandes, Georg, 1915 (1)
  - Breitscheid, Dr. Rud., 1914 (1)
  - Brentano, Lujo, 1915 (1)
  - Beaulieu, Heloise von, 1917 (1)
  - Bergmann, 1918 (1)
  - Birukoff, Paul, 1918 (1)
  - Curtiss, 1915 (1)
  - Dernburg, 1915 (1)
  - Diner-Denes, Josef (?), 1918 (1)
  - Dumeril, Edmond, 1915 (1)
  - Dunsberg, C., 1918 (1)
  - Eeden, Frederik von, 1915 (2)
  - Flake, Otto, 1918-1919 (4)
  - Foerster, Friedrich Wilhelm, 1914-1917 (7)
  - Frank, Leonhard, n.d. (2)
  - Frankenburg, von, n.d. (1)
  - Fried, Oskar, 1919 (1)
  - Fielitz, Axel von, 1918 (1)
  - Gothein, 1914-1918 (3)
  - Giesswein, Dr. Alexander, 1915 (1)
  - Gruenberg, Dr. Carl, 1915-1917 (3)
  - Heath, Carl, 1914 (1)
  - Hertz, Fr., 1915 (1)
  - Huber, Max, 1916 (2)
  - Haeberlin, Hermann, 1915 (1)
  - Hauptmann, Carl, 1915 (1)
  - Herzog, Wilhelm, 1915 (1)
  - Husby, Karl (?), 1915 (1)
  - Jaccard, Dr. Paul, 1917 (1)
  - Kanner (Heinrich), 1918 (1)
  - Kemeny, Fr., 1911 (1)
  - Kinkel, Prof., 1915 (1)
  - Klabund (Henschke, Alfred), 1918 (3)
  - Krestanoff, Ivan, 1917 (1)
  - Lammasch, Prof. Heinrich, 1915(?)-1917 (11)
  - Lange, Chr. L., 1917 (1)
  - Lardy (?), 1918 (1)
  - Latzko, Andreas, 1918 (2)
  - Laun, Dr. Rudolf, 1915 (1)
  - Le Foyer, Lucien (?), n.d. (1)
  - Lehmann-Russbueldt, Otto, 1915 (1)
  - Leonhardt (?), 1917 (1)
  - Leyden, C. (?), n.d., (1)
  - Lichtheim, Prof., 1917 (1)
  - Marschall, Adolf von (?), 1914 (1)
  - Marshall (?), 1915 (1)
  - de Mathies, P., 1917-1918 (2)
  - Mehring, Sigmar, 1915 (1)
  - Melichar, A.G. (?), 1917 (1)
  - Merey. v. Kapos-Mere, 1917-1918 (2)
  - Meyer, G.W., 1915 (1)
  - Mickels, Robert (?), 1917 (2)
  - Miyaoka, Tsunejiro, 1915 (1)
  - Moscheles, Felix, 1919 (1)
  - Muehlon, Wilhelm, 1917 (2)
  - Natorp, Paul, 1915 (2)
  - de Neufville, Eduard de, 1900 (1)
  - Neumann, Erich (?), 1915 (1)
  - Nippold, Otfried, 1915 (2)
  - Nithack-Stahn, 1915 (1)
  - Nordau, Dr. M., 1914-1916 (4)
  - Persius, L., 1914-1916 (2)
  - Popper, Josef, 1915 (1)
  - Rolland, Romain, 1915-1918 (5)
  - Rogat, L. (?), 1918 (2)
  - Rösemeir (?), 1918 (1)
  - Roulatin, Dr. N., 1916 (1)
  - Ruhiness, Ludwig, 1918 (2)
  - Ruyne, Theodore (?), 1916 (1)
  - Said-Ruete, R., 1918 (1)
  - Scherrer-Fuellemann, J., 1915 (2)
  - Schickele, Rene, 1916-1919 (2)
  - Schlieffen, Graf, 1916 (1)
  - Schuecking, Walther, 1917 (1)
  - Schwantje, Magnus, 1914 (1)
  - Seatini, L. (?), 1919 (1)
  - Seiffer, P. (?), 1918 (1)
  - Staudinger, F., 1915 (1)
  - Stilgebauer, Edward, 1918 (3)
  - Stroebel, Heinrich, 1917 (2)
  - Sturm, August (?), n.d. (1)
  - Sybel, Ludwig von, 1916 (2)
  - Szazad, Huszadik, 1915 (1)
  - Teuer, E.P. (?), 1915 (1)
  - Umfrid, O., 1914 (1)
  - Verdene, Georges, 1916 (1)
  - Verein von Kinderfreunden, 1915 (1)
  - Waltershaufen, A. Sartorius von, 1915 (1)
  - Webb, Sydney, 1915-1916 (3)
  - Weingartner, Felix von, 1917-1918 (2)
  - Wolff, Theodor, 1918 (1)
  - Wrangel, F. von, 1915 (1)
  - Zurlinden, 1919 (1)
  - Zweig, Stefan, 1918 (4)
- WRITINGS, ca. 1910-1919
  - Untitled, n.d., Holograph (Box 4)
  - "Pariser Voelkerbundvertrag," (Pact of the League of Nations), n.d., Holograph
  - "Die sittlichen Werte and die Kulturbedeutung der Cholera," (The moral worth and cultural meaning of cholera), n.d., Typescript, carbon copy
- SUBJECT FILE, 1914-1919
  - "Dokumente zur 'Grossen Zeit'" (Documents of the 'Grand Era'), Clippings (Box 4)
  - "Krieg- und Friedensziele" (Aims of Peace and War), Clippings
    - "Berner Zusammenkunft zur Besprechung der Gestaltung der Voelkerbeziehung nach dem Krieg" (The Bern Assembly for the discussion of the form of international relations after the war), 1917., Printed pamphlet
    - "Sollen Wir Annektieren?" (Should we annex?), 1915., Printed pamphlet
  - "Kuriose Abbildungen, Karikaturen, usw" (Curious Representations, Caricatures, etc.), Clippings
  - "Oesterreich-Ungarns Todesurteile" (Austria-Hungary, Decline), Clippings
  - "Schuldfrage" (European War, 1914-1918, Responsibility for), Clippings (2 folders)
    - Bernstoff, Count J.H. von, "Germany and the Great War," ca. 1914., Article, printed copy (Box 5)
    - Breitscheid, Rud., "Vor Fuenf Jahren," (Five years ago), 1919., Article, printed copy
    - "Briefwechsel Zwischen den Heeren Guyot und Bellet and Heern Lujo Brentano," (Correspondence between Misters Guyot and Bellet and Mister Lujo Brentano), 1914., Pamphlet, 2 c.
    - Heilmann, Graff Ernst, "Die 'Emser Depesche' von 1914 fabriziert von franzoesischen Sozialdemokraten," (The 'Emser Dispatch' of 1914, fabricated by French Social Democrats), 1916., Article, printed copy
    - Hertz, Dr. Friedrich, "Die Entstehung des Weltkrieges," (The outbreak of the world war), 1919., Article, printed copy
    - "Der Krieg," (The war), author unknown. Excerpt, Die Zukunft, August 1, 1914., Printed copy
    - Montgelas, Graf Max, "Die Mobilmachungen des Jahres 1914," (The mobilizations of 1914), 1919., Article, printed copy
    - Muehlon, Wilhelm, "Zur Wahrheit," (To the truth), 1918., Article, printed and carbon copies
    - "Nein oder Ja?," (No or yes?), author unknown. Excerpt, Die Zukunft, July 21, 1919., Printed copy
    - Popert, Hermann, "Die Schuld am Weltkrieg," (The responsibility for the world war), 1919., Article, printed copy
    - Rieger, Franz, "Conrads Vermessenheit," (Conrad's arrogance), 1919., Article, printed copy
    - "Das unsichtbare Kaiserreich," n.d. German translation of David Starr Jordan's Unseen Empire, with introduction and comments., Handwritten copy
    - "Vor dem Weltgericht," (Before the world court), author unknown. Excerpt, Die Zukunft, March 29, 1919., Printed copy
    - "Wir Vergessen Nicht," (We do not forget), author unknown. Excerpt, Die Zukunft, September 6, 1919., Printed copy
  - "Voelkerbund" (League of Nations), Clippings
  - "Voelkerrecht, Greuel, Hass..." (International law, Horror, Hate...)
    - Clippings
    - "Dokumente der Schmach: Die Deutsche Regierung als Anstifterin des Hoch- und Landesverrats," (Documents of disgrace: The German government as instigator of high treason), 1917., Article, printed copy
- MISCELLANY
  - Scrapbook on Bertha von Suttner, ca. 1900-1914., One volume, bound (Box 5)